<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" type="xml"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="chap-intro">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-intro-welcome">
        <title>Welcome</title>
        <para>The Internet and the World Wide Web have changed mankind, forever. It is to early too
            tell, but their impact may be as great as the combustion engine or the introduction of
            electric devices. The Internet gave universal access to information, not just
            information that broadcasters or newspapers thought that was important, but information
            that interests the 'websurfer'. However the Internet is not a one-way street, every
            Internet user is also a producer: people make websites, maintain blogs, post tweets, and
            socialize via social networks.</para>
        <para>Since a substantial part of the world has Internet access, and every user is also a
            producer, there is an enormous amount of information available. Some of it is of
            peer-reviewed and of a high quality, most of it is unchecked and biased. Still, every
            single piece of information can contain valuable information. For instance, as a vacuum
            cleaner producer, you might think that social media are not so interesting. However, the
            contrary is true: between billions of messages there may be hundreds expressing
            sentiment about your product. Such messages can answer questions about how your brand is
            conceived, what problems people commonly have with your product, etc.</para>
        <para>Obviously, it is out of anyone's reach to manually analyze a significant portion of
            the information that is available on the Internet. The amount is just too overwhelming.
            Classic data analysis tools may not suffice either, most of the information is seemingly
            unstructured, and consist of blobs of natural language sentences. However, language is
            also structure. It is just not the kind of structure that computers can normally deal
            with. Computers deal with neat XML files, fragments of JSON, or comma separated values.
            No, it is the structure that we humans use to convey and transfer meaning. This book is
            about that type of information. We will go into many of the techniques that so-called
                <emphasis role="italic">computational linguists</emphasis> use to analyze the
            structure of human language, and transform it into a form that computers work
            with.</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-intro-whats-nlp">
        <title>What is natural language processing?</title>
        <para>Stub</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-intro-whats-haskell">
        <title>What is Ruby?</title>
        <para>Todo</para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1 xml:id="sec-intro-needs">
        <title>What you need</title>
        <para>Some examples in the book use corpora. These corpora are available at: <link
                xlink:href="http://nlpwp.org/">http://nlpwp.org/</link></para>
    </sect1>
    <sect1>
        <title>Ready, set, go!</title>
        <para>If you are not familiar with the <command>irb</command> interactive Ruby interpreter,
            it may be a good idea too play around with it. This book will make extensive use of it
            to gradually build classes and methods. On UNIX systems, type <command>irb</command> in
            a terminal to launch the interpreter. You will be greeted with a prompt that resembles
            the following:<screen>$ <userinput>irb</userinput>
>></screen></para>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
